Finding Aid for the Allen Dean Palmer collection on Heinrich Marschner. PASC-M.0077
UCLA Library Special Collections
Allen Dean Palmer collection on Heinrich Marschner
1831-1987
UCLA Library Special Collections
Palmer, A. Dean
PASC-M.0077
1.2 Linear Feet (2 flat boxes and 1 document box)
This collection contains research material pertaining to German composer and music director Heinrich Marschner, compiled by Allen Dean Palmer during his studies at UCLA. Material includes photographs, printed sheet music, clippings, postcards, and Palmer's completed Masters thesis and PhD dissertation.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charlotte S. Myers and Allen Dean Palmer, 1988.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922213293606533
Biography/History
HEINRICH AUGUST MARSCHNER (born 16 August 1795) was a German composer who served as Kapellmeister at the Hanover court opera for thirty years. He is primarily known for his operas, though he was a romantic composer who also made important contributions to the Lied, or body of German Romantic poems set to classical music.
Though Marschner, who was born in Zittau, showed early promise as a soprano and a pianoforte player, he moved to Leipzig in 1913 with the intention of studying law. Convinced to make music his profession, he travelled in 1816 with Count Thaddaus von Amadee, to Pressburg and Vienna, where he made the acquaintance of Ludwig Van Beethoven. Settling in Pressburg, he wrote three operas, including Heinrich IV und Aubigne, which was produced in 1820. He was consequently appointed Kapellmeister of the German and Italian opera there, in 1823. He was appointed Musikdirector in 1824, but resigned and relocated to Leipzig, where he settled in 1827 as Kapellmeister of the theater. There he produced Der Vampyr (1828), a successful opera which was also given in 1829 at the Lyceum Theatre in London, running for sixty nights.
In 1831, he was appointed court Kapellmeister at Hanover. He produced Hans Heiling in 1833; this is widely considered his masterwork, and enjoyed great success. In 1836 it was performed under his own direction in Copenhagen; consequently, he was offered the post of General Musical Director in Denmark, which he declined in order to remain in Hanover. Kaiser Adolf von Nassau was produced at Dresden in 1845 under Richard Wagner's conductorship. In 1859, he was pensioned at the theater with the title of Generalmusikdirector. Marschner died on 14 December 1861, in Hanover. A monument was erected to his memory there in 1877.
ALLEN DEAN PALMER was a student of music at UCLA who wrote his Master of Arts thesis, Heinrich Marschner and his Opera, "Der Vampyr", in 1975. His PhD dissertation, Heinrich August Marschner (1795-1861) and His Stage Works, was approved in 1978.
Scope and Content
This collection contains research material pertaining to German composer and music director Heinrich Marschner, compiled by Allen Dean Palmer during his studies at UCLA. Material includes photographs, printed sheet music, clippings, postcards, and Palmer's completed Masters thesis and PhD dissertation. All scores are composed by Heinrich Marschner, unless otherwise noted.
Scores.; Composers -- Portraits.; Composers -- Germany.; Marschner, Heinrich
- Portrait engraving of Marschner (framed, with annotations), circa 1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Portrait photograph of Marschner, circa 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Carte de visite portrait of Marschner, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Portrait photograph of Marschner's great- granddaughter Marianna Stahl (bears annotations), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Portrait photograph of Toni Marschner, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photograph of Marschner's monument in Zittau, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photograph of Marschner's bust in Vienna State Opera (with annotations), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photograph of Hanover opera house (with annotations), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Postcard of Hanover opera house, addressed to Augusta Marschner, circa 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Postcard of Hanover opera house, addressed to Marianna Stahl, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ave Maria. Photocopy of vocal score, in copyist's hand, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Hans Heiling, "An Jenam Tag" aria. Vocal scores, circa 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  General
  Published Otto Forberg, Leipzig
- Hans Heiling, "An Jenam Tag" aria. Vocal scores, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Published by B. Schott, Mainz
- Romanze for piano, violin, and violoncello. Score with parts, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Published by Friedrich Hermann, editions C.F. Peters, Leipzig
- Schon Ella. Photocopy of vocal score, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Published by Friedrich Hofmeister, Leipzig
- Der Templer und de Judin. Photocopy of opera score, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Published by Freidrich Hofmeister, Leipzig
- Bound collection of various printed scores, belonging to Toni Marschner, 1844-1850 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Scope and Content
  Includes "The Indian Carnival" by Anthony Philip Heinrich (dedicated to Marschner), "The Museum Polka" by Anthony Philip Heinrich (inscribed to Jenny Lind), "Mym Slovanskym Bratrum V Europe" by Anthony Philip Heinrich, "Quatre Caprices Pour Le Piano" by J.P.E. Hartmann (dedicated to Marschner), "Qatrieme Rondeau pour Piano" by Adolphe Hesse, "Grande Sonate pour le Pianoforte" by Fr. W. Crund (dedicated to Marschner), "Hommage A Beethover" by Charles Czerny, and "Romance Sans Paroles" and "Nocturne pour le Piano" by Adlophe Hesse
- The Cadeau: a Christmas, New Year's, Midsummer, or Birth-day Present for 1831. Songbook by F.W.N. Bayley and W. Neuland (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Berühmte Musiker (Famous Musicians), Vol. XII: Heinrich Marschner, by Georg Munzer, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Original cover and title page; photocopied contents. With annotations.
- Vienna State Opera printed brochure (with annotations), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Clippings from German newspaper, circa 1877 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Ovation: The Magazine for Classical Music Listeners, Vol.5, No.8, 1984 September (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Research material, circa 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Includes images cut from a book, an inventory, and photocopies of reference entries and articles about Marschner.
- Heinrich Marschner and His Opera, Der Vampyr. Palmer M.A. thesis., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Heinrich Marschner (1795-1861) and His Stage Works. Palmer PhD dissertation., 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)